A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of Communications, Vice President, Office Files of Alex Wilde FA1892
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of Communications, Vice President, Office Files of Alex Wilde
1962-2004
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Wilde, Alexander
FA1892
3.23 Cubic Feet 9 document boxes: 8 letter boxes and 1 half-letter box
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
This material was transferred to the RAC in four accessions between 2021 and 2024 and was ingested by the RAC as Accessions 2021:091, 2021:111, 2023:048, and 2024:011.
Arrangement
Collection is comprised of one series.
Original order was maintained as much as possible.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject files, 1962-2004
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the office files Alexander, "Alex", Wilde created when he served as Vice President of the Ford Foundation's Office of Communications. The collection consists of one series of subject files.
While the collection primarily holds files from Wilde's position as Communications Vice President, there are also some materials Wilde created during his previous role as Foundation Representative for the Andean Region and Southern Cone when he was based in the Santiago, Chile Office. Some Communications related files originate from before Wilde became Vice President. They document a broader time frame of the Communications Office's strategy and activities.
Wilde's files provide insight into the Office of Communications' activities and challenges during the early 2000s. They concern the Foundation's communications strategy during a period of increased scrutiny of private foundations following the September 11 World Trade Center attack in 2001. They also document the Foundation's actions to keep pace with media trends of the time such as through the development of its website. Other records regard Communications Office responsibilities for Foundation publication preparation and dissemination, media coverage and relations, and advising Foundation executive staff on public statements.
Common material formats found within the collection include correspondence, memos, notes, drafts, reports, articles, news clippings, press releases, publications, speech transcripts, and meeting materials. There are a few pieces of Wilde's writings and a couple photographs.
Ford Foundation; Public relations
- Subject files, 1962-2004; 1; 3.23 Cubic Feet 9 document boxes: 8 letter boxes and 1 half-letter box
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the subject files Alexander, "Alex", Wilde created and maintained while he served as Vice President of the Ford Foundation's Office of Communications. It includes some files Wilde inherited from before he became Communications Vice President and a few files he created in his earlier position as Foundation Representative for the Andean Region and Southern Cone at the Santiago, Chile Office.
  Wilde's Communications Office files document the Foundation's media response and strategy during a period of controversy for private foundations in the early 2000s. Events like the fallout from the United Nations World Conference on Racism in Durban, South Africa, public scrutiny of foundations and charities' giving practices after the September 11 World Trade Center attack in 2001, and the proposed House of Representative Bill 7 regarding private foundations' annual contributions to charities concerned the Communications Office's public relations work. Materials show that, at this same time, the Communications Office worked to keep the Foundation's public relations tools current with contemporary media trends through branding and the Foundation's public website. Other activities documented in the series include broader communications strategy development, Foundation publication preparation and dissemination, media coverage of Foundation activities, and support for Foundation executive staff on developing public statements. Wilde's files include his correspondence, notes, and a few of his writings.
  There are files from Wilde's transition from Representative for the Andean Region and Southern Cone to the Communications Office. Some of these files pertain to his activities in the Santiago Office. Other materials from before Wilde's tenure as Communications Vice President give evidence of a longer history of communications strategy and public relations projects at the Foundation.
  - Innovations in American Government Awards - Media coverage and communications plan, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Innovations in American Government Awards - Media coverage, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Innovations in American Government Awards - Media coverage, 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Ford Foundation 1996 Annual Report - September 10, 1996 Discussion Paper (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ford Foundation 1996 Annual Report - Memos (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ford Foundation 1996 Annual Report - Sundberg and Associates presentation (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ford Foundation 1996 Annual Report - Sisco and Evans design, 1996-1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ford Foundation 1996 Annual Report - 1995 Annual Report (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Ford Foundation 1996 Annual Report - Drafts, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Ford Foundation 1996 Annual Report - Correspondence and memos, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Ford Foundation 1996 Annual Report - Susan Berresford Message, circa 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Irruptions of Memory: Expressive Politics in Chile's Transition to Democracy - Alex Wilde, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Alex Wilde articles, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Alex Wilde book - Conversaciones de Caballeros, 1982-2000 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Time Magazine - The New Philanthropists, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Vector III Task Force on Grant Making, Monitoring, and Accountability, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Ford Foundation at a Glance, 2002-2004 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Ford Foundation Strategic Communications Initiative - Thea Lurie drafts and notes, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Ford Foundation March 2004 Program Leadership Meeting - Communications Session (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Ford Foundation 2003 Annual Report - Proposed edits, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Save Zimbabwe Campaign, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - MACE-DELTA - Notes, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - January 2000 Worldwide Philanthropy Group Meeting (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - NGO accountability, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Office of Communications mission, 1997-2000 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Ford Foundation President Susan Berresford statements, articles, and speaking appearances, 1998-2003 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Communications - Media coverage about Palestinian grantees, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Ford Foundation President Susan Berresford statement regarding United Nation World Conference on Racism in Durban, South Africa - Drafts, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - United States Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) and Ford Foundation November 2000 joint media release - Ford Foundation internship program (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - United States Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) - Manning Selvage and Lee (MSL) media response, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Ford Foundation diversity profile - New York Times, 1987-2000 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Millennium Challenge Account (MCA) - InterAction, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Millennium Challenge Account (MCA) - Susan Berresford March 2003 testimony to United States Senate Foreign Relations Committee (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Millennium Challenge Account (MCA) - InterAction, 2001-2003 (Box 4, Folder 36-37)
  - Millennium Challenge Account (MCA) - InterAction, 2001-2003 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Harvard University Joint Center for Housing Studies June 2000 press release, 1999-2003 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Ford Foundation October-November 2002 Joint Worldwide Meeting, 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - United States Senate Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, part 1, 1983-1992 (Box 4, Folder 41-42)
  - United States Senate Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, part 2, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Media notes regarding United States House of Representatives Bill 7 and foundation accountability, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - United States House of Representatives Bill 7 Communications Committee - Council on Foundations, 2003-2004 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Philanthropy, Accountability, and Social Justice - Bradford K. Smith, Bologna, Italy, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Chuck Grassley - United States Senate Finance Committee, 2002-2004 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Foundation accountability - Stephanie Strom, New York Times, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Foundation accountability and anti-terrorist financing guidelines, 2000-2003 (Box 5, Folder 49-50)
  - Alex Wilde 2000-2004 outgoing correspondence (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Ford Foundation regional issues - Reports, articles, notes, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Office of Communications meetings with Vice Presidents, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Office of Communications staff retreats, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Strategic Communications Handbook draft outline, 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Office of Communications staff lunch meetings, 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Strategic communications - Strategy for Impact, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Communications planning - Ford Foundation Report (FFR) dissemination (David Anderson and Thea Lurie), 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Office of Communications May 2003 Staff Retreat, 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - December 2003 Program Officer Orientation, 2001-2003 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - December 2002 Program Officer Orientation - Office of Communications lunch (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Ford Foundation publications - Correspondence, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Ford Foundation program related and occasional publications - Policies and guidelines, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Catch-up meetings with Susan Berresford, 2003-2004 (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - KIT-CAB, 2003-2004 (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Ford Foundation June 2004 Vice Presidents Retreat, 1992-2004 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Children's Savings Accounts Initiative communications, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Ford Foundation branding, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous materials - Office of Communications and Santiago, Chile Office, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Websites, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Aspen Institute Congressional Program March-April 2002 Conference on United States-China Relations, 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - Aspen Institute Congressional Program January 2002 Conference on Islam, Terrorism, and the United States Response, Punta Mita, Mexico, 2001-2002 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Aspen Institute/Ford Foundation March 2001 International Roundtable on Journalism, Santiago, Chile, 2000-2001; File contains one still image (Box 6, Folder 73)
    File contains a photograph. The photograph depicts a group at the International Roundtable of Journalism and Freedom of Expression in Santiago, Chile. Alex Wilde is in the photograph.
    There is a caption on the back of the photograph. It identifies the individuals in the photograph.
  - Aspen Institute Congressional Seminar April 2001 Conference on United States-China Relations - Cancelled (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Alex Wilde transition to Office of Communications - Public opinion of philanthropy and Ford Foundation press, 1990-1999; File contains one still image (Box 7, Folder 75-77)
    File contains a photograph. The photograph is of Ford Foundation President Susan Berresford.
    There is a caption on the back of the photograph. The photograph is dated March 1996, and the credit belongs to Ben Russell.
  - Ford Foundation 1999 communications assessment, 1962-1999 (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Susan Berresford speeches, part 1, 1996-2002 (Box 7, Folder 79-80)
  - Susan Berresford speeches, part 2, 1996-2001 (Box 8, Folder 81)
  - Alex Wilde notes and other materials, 1999-2001 (Box 8, Folder 82-84)
  - Burning Patience: A Brief History of the Ford Foundation's Work in the Andean Region and the Southern Cone (1962-2002) - Christopher Reardon, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - Alan Divack - John Bresnan chapter about Ford Foundation Indonesia program, undated (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - Program budget notes, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - Alex Wilde notes, 2003-2004 (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - Internal Ford Foundation meetings - Notes, 2001-2002 (Box 8, Folder 89)
  - Ford Foundation communications strategy development, 1996-2000 (Box 8, Folder 90)
  - Foundations and charities response to September 11 World Trade Center attack, 2001-2002 (Box 8, Folder 91)
  - Miscellaneous notes and correspondence, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 92)
  - Lloyd Garrison - Ford Foundation History Project, 1982-1996 (Box 9, Folder 93)